<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: crowd-sourcing | Kate Chapman - Maploser]]></title>
  <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/categories/crowd-sourcing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://maploser.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-30T16:49:41+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://maploser.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kate Chapman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crowd funding Satellite Imagery]]></title>
    <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/2012/03/18/crowd-funding-satellite-imagery/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-18T03:59:22+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://maploser.com/blog/2012/03/18/crowd-funding-satellite-imagery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have discussed the need for <a href="http://www.maploser.com/2011/07/06/imagery-pre-disaster-lets-do-better/">access to satellite information</a> for <a href="http://www.maploser.com/2010/11/16/openstreetmap-and-crisis-response-why-it-is-sometimes-about-the-license/">crisis response often</a>. When there is a large scale disaster imagery tends to become available relatively quickly, but in cases of smaller events or mapping for preparedness this is not always the case. In my work in Indonesia over the past year we have been fortunate to be able to purchase imagery of <a href="http://tasks.hotosm.org/job/9">Padang City</a> (OpenStreetMap login required) and additionally Microsoft has updated much of the imagery available through Bing Maps. This access has been enabled by the purchasing power of large organizations, AusAID and Microsoft respectively. Work continues to use similarly sized organizations to increase access in other areas, but the process is slow and there is no guarantee imagery will be available everywhere, every time. Yet. Currently the digitization of the imagery is performed by the crowd, what about enabling them to assist in the purchase?</p>

<h2>Lack of Physical or Financial Access</h2>

<p>The<a href="http://publiclaboratory.org/"> Public Laboratory for Open Science and Technology</a> (PLOTS) has done much to enable the crowd-sourcing of inexpensive imagery. Unfortunately many times when crisis mapping occurs access to collect this type of imagery is impossible or extremely dangerous. Imagine flying a balloon in Syria today in order to collect information, the risks would be suicidal.  In other cases the physical terrain of the area may make it very difficult to access, but a small group may not have the financial means to purchase imagery by other means.</p>

<h2>Enabling Collective Purchasing Power</h2>

<p>Currently the <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a> utilizes a tool the <a href="http://tasks.hotosm.org/">Tasking Manager</a> to coordinate digitization and verification of imagery analysis. What if this tool could also be utilized to feed into the purchase process of imagery. Individuals could choose to adopt squares and volunteer to pay for them, this would be an all or nothing proposition, if all the squares were pledge the project would go forward, otherwise it would not. This crowd-funding model would be very similar to <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/">Kickstarter</a>, but perhaps instead of rewards pledgers could adopt squares to digitize once the imagery was purchased.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.maploser.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/padang_sized.png"><img src="http://www.maploser.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/padang_sized.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The image above is the overview map from the Tasking Manager of the task for Padang City.  It gives a quick overview of Total number of jobs, how many jobs are done, how many are validated and how many are currently being worked on.  What if there was an overview of squares that were funded?  The same as when someone takes a job to complete they could either select a random job or a specific one by clicking on the map.  The entire community would be able to see quickly if an area was near being available for purchase.</p>

<p>In Kickstarter it is possible for projects to collect more than they ask for initially.  If people were adopting specific squares I don't see this being possible, but perhaps if you selected a random square they would not be assigned to the end.  That way it would be possible for more squares to be purchased than exist.  Sponsors of the imagery fundraising drive could decide on specific things that would happen in these cases (ahead of time to encourage the crowd), possible ideas would be:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>purchase of GPS units to create a bank for people living in those areas</p></li>
<li><p>a HOT mission to train those locally how to map in OpenStreetMap</p></li>
<li><p>Purchase of imagery of an expanded area</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Can We Expand Access to Imagery?</h2>

<p>I will continue to advocate for expansion of access to imagery. <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/schuyler">Schuyler Erle</a> has previously stated that access to imagery in times of crisis is vital almost like water for mapping in response (Schuyler sorry I couldn't find an exact quote). I fully agree with this assessment. I will continue to work with governments and large organizations with purchasing power that can help enable the crowd to respond.  If imagery is as vital as water though, I think we also have to take matters into our own hands as pursue every avenue possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Authoritating Data - What Makes Some Data Authoritative?]]></title>
    <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/2011/02/16/authoritating-data/"/>
    <updated>2011-02-16T05:01:24+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://maploser.com/blog/2011/02/16/authoritating-data</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As I <a href="http://blog.fortiusone.com/2011/02/14/our-trip-to-redlands-gis-week/">wrote about</a> in the <a href="http://fortiusone.com/">FortiusOne</a> blog, last week was <a href="http://redlandsgisweek.org/">Redlands GIS Week</a>.  My post there concentrated more on the future of crowd-sourced geographic data in crisis response and ways to more quickly turn that data into information.  That is something that I've spent quite of bit of time thinking about through my work on <a href="http://geocommons.com/">GeoCommon</a>s, as well as my work with the <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org/weblog/">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a>.  I spent so much time thinking about enabling crowd-sourcing of information and teaching people to edit in <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/">OpenStreetMap</a> that something I've never thought much about is the stamping of data to make it authoritative.  During a break-out group at GIS Week we were supposed to discuss 'the Issues with VGI."  Nothing really new to me as far as issues came out of the discussion, one realization did occur was I have previously made data authoritative or authoritating it as I have started saying tongue in cheek.</p>

<p>I think part of the reason I've never really thought about this is that to me data is either authoritative or it is not, but that isn't what determines how I use it.  One of the previous jobs I had was doing data quality assurance, during that time I found many errors in that is considered authoritative data.  Because of this previous job I have a lot of experience evaluating data.  Everyone should do some evaluation of data before they use it, but it really depends on the type and the source how much they actually need to do.  In thinking about this evaluation I began to think about the process of when we "qa'd" data before it was delivered to customers.  Essentially that QA process was making data authoritative.  What we were actually doing to create the data was not much different from the crowd-source efforts of many groups today though.</p>

<p>There was usually an expert in the field we were creating datasets for who would figure out what to be collected.  The majority of the actual research though was done by interns or recent college grads.  These people scoured the internet mostly, but would occasionally call to confirm information.  Once a new dataset was created or an old one updated it would go through a quality assurance process.  Much of this was running automated tools to look for data that did not conform to what was expected.  For example geocodes in the wrong state/zip, phone numbers of the wrong length and comparing the new data to old when possible.  Then we would manually look for errors in the data.  Once we decided information was "good enough" it would be pushed out to customers.  This is the point where the data became "authoritative."  In the whole data creation process I estimate each dataset was touched between two and one hundred sets of hands.  Two if the expert created the dataset by themselves and then one person tested it.  One hundred if the dataset had been around through multiple updates that large groups of people worked on.  If you compare this to the number of hands datasets from the CrisisMappers list, such as the recent mapping of polling stations in Sudan or the road data for OpenStreetMap the authoritative data hasn't even been gone through as thoroughly as the non-authoritative data source.   Also if a mistake was found in the authoritative data source it would have to be updated and go through the whole quality assurance process again.  What really is the difference between the two types of data in this case?</p>

<p>To me, really just that a company put their name on the authoritative data.  I suppose if you are a buyer of the data you would have some recourse if there was a problem with the information.  You could probably ask for all or some portion of your money back, if things went really wrong you could sue.  Though in my examples I believe the crowd-sourced information had been more reviewed, so perhaps the chance of having issue with it is less. I realize this comparison does not work in the case of all datasets, though it is something to think about when discrediting crowd-sourced data. From where did your authoritative data come?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
