<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Crisis Mapping | Kate Chapman - Maploser]]></title>
  <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/categories/crisis-mapping/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-30T16:01:26+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kate Chapman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Crowd funding Satellite Imagery]]></title>
    <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2012/03/18/crowd-funding-satellite-imagery/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-18T03:59:22+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2012/03/18/crowd-funding-satellite-imagery</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have discussed the need for <a href="http://www.maploser.com/2011/07/06/imagery-pre-disaster-lets-do-better/">access to satellite information</a> for <a href="http://www.maploser.com/2010/11/16/openstreetmap-and-crisis-response-why-it-is-sometimes-about-the-license/">crisis response often</a>. When there is a large scale disaster imagery tends to become available relatively quickly, but in cases of smaller events or mapping for preparedness this is not always the case. In my work in Indonesia over the past year we have been fortunate to be able to purchase imagery of <a href="http://tasks.hotosm.org/job/9">Padang City</a> (OpenStreetMap login required) and additionally Microsoft has updated much of the imagery available through Bing Maps. This access has been enabled by the purchasing power of large organizations, AusAID and Microsoft respectively. Work continues to use similarly sized organizations to increase access in other areas, but the process is slow and there is no guarantee imagery will be available everywhere, every time. Yet. Currently the digitization of the imagery is performed by the crowd, what about enabling them to assist in the purchase?</p>

<h2>Lack of Physical or Financial Access</h2>

<p>The<a href="http://publiclaboratory.org/"> Public Laboratory for Open Science and Technology</a> (PLOTS) has done much to enable the crowd-sourcing of inexpensive imagery. Unfortunately many times when crisis mapping occurs access to collect this type of imagery is impossible or extremely dangerous. Imagine flying a balloon in Syria today in order to collect information, the risks would be suicidal.  In other cases the physical terrain of the area may make it very difficult to access, but a small group may not have the financial means to purchase imagery by other means.</p>

<h2>Enabling Collective Purchasing Power</h2>

<p>Currently the <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a> utilizes a tool the <a href="http://tasks.hotosm.org/">Tasking Manager</a> to coordinate digitization and verification of imagery analysis. What if this tool could also be utilized to feed into the purchase process of imagery. Individuals could choose to adopt squares and volunteer to pay for them, this would be an all or nothing proposition, if all the squares were pledge the project would go forward, otherwise it would not. This crowd-funding model would be very similar to <a href="http://www.kickstarter.com/">Kickstarter</a>, but perhaps instead of rewards pledgers could adopt squares to digitize once the imagery was purchased.</p>

<p><a href="http://www.maploser.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/padang_sized.png"><img src="http://www.maploser.com/wp-content/uploads/2012/03/padang_sized.png" alt="" /></a></p>

<p>The image above is the overview map from the Tasking Manager of the task for Padang City.  It gives a quick overview of Total number of jobs, how many jobs are done, how many are validated and how many are currently being worked on.  What if there was an overview of squares that were funded?  The same as when someone takes a job to complete they could either select a random job or a specific one by clicking on the map.  The entire community would be able to see quickly if an area was near being available for purchase.</p>

<p>In Kickstarter it is possible for projects to collect more than they ask for initially.  If people were adopting specific squares I don't see this being possible, but perhaps if you selected a random square they would not be assigned to the end.  That way it would be possible for more squares to be purchased than exist.  Sponsors of the imagery fundraising drive could decide on specific things that would happen in these cases (ahead of time to encourage the crowd), possible ideas would be:</p>

<ul>
<li><p>purchase of GPS units to create a bank for people living in those areas</p></li>
<li><p>a HOT mission to train those locally how to map in OpenStreetMap</p></li>
<li><p>Purchase of imagery of an expanded area</p></li>
</ul>


<h2>Can We Expand Access to Imagery?</h2>

<p>I will continue to advocate for expansion of access to imagery. <a href="https://twitter.com/#!/schuyler">Schuyler Erle</a> has previously stated that access to imagery in times of crisis is vital almost like water for mapping in response (Schuyler sorry I couldn't find an exact quote). I fully agree with this assessment. I will continue to work with governments and large organizations with purchasing power that can help enable the crowd to respond.  If imagery is as vital as water though, I think we also have to take matters into our own hands as pursue every avenue possible.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Book Sprints for Humanitarian Response]]></title>
    <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2011/10/23/book-sprints-for-humanitarian-response/"/>
    <updated>2011-10-23T02:52:56+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2011/10/23/book-sprints-for-humanitarian-response</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the past week I've been at Google in Mountain View working on a book sprint for OpenStreetMap.  I had no idea when the week started that we were going to write a book in a week, nor that it was possible to do that.  I also wasn't familiar with <a href="http://flossmanuals.net/">FLOSS Manuals</a> which operates under the premise that not only should software be open and free but the documentation should be as well.</p>

<p>The premise of the week was to bring individuals from open-source projects together as well as others specializing in documentation in as well to help.  A combination of an unconference and then intensive documentation writing ensued.  The OpenStreetMap group included Ian Dees, Shaun McDonald and myself from the project.  We additionally had Anne Goldenberg, Anne Gentle, Tomi Toivio and Nóirín Plunkett.  Having so many people from outside OpenStreetMap was extremely valuable.  They were able to help us be far more clear about the materials and see past assumptions we may have made about topics.  At the end we had a published book, which <a href="http://www.lulu.com/product/paperback/openstreetmap/18173430">can be purchased from Lulu.com</a>. Having a completed work at the end of the sprint was a great feeling.  Often after hackathons that is missing for me and it ends up feeling like we just flogged ourselves with some code for a set period of time.</p>

<p>In going through this process I started to think about other topics that could benefit from this type of approach.  I started thinking about the topics that we go over repeatedly within the Humanitarian Open-Source, CrisisMappers and Volunteer Technology Communities (for lack of a better name).  I really think the community could benefit from a generic guide to issues within the humanitarian technology realm.  Topics such as standards, licensing and workflows could be documented.  It is impossible to say what exactly the book would cover, because that is determined as part of the book sprint process.  What I am proposing though is that it would be greatly beneficial to gather for this process.</p>

<p>Typically a book sprint would happen over roughly a week time with five to ten individuals with different experience on the topic.  I'm proposing the same thing. Let's plan a book sprint and figure out how to make it happen.  The idea would be to gather about ten people with different experience, everything from technologists to humanitarian responders to specialists in documentation.  This group would get together for an intensive week long book sprint, the goal being to create a manual of the basics of humanitarian technology.  Topics that come to mind for me are data licensing, standards, security, privacy and workflows.  I'm only one individual and I'm sure topics would change and mold to the importance decided on by the group.  The point though would be to create a resource useful within our community.</p>

<p>Does this sound interesting to you?  Contact me in the comments or by email and let's make it happen!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disaster 2.0, Innovation in the Disaster Response Space]]></title>
    <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2011/03/29/disaster-2-0-innovation-in-the-disaster-response-space/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-29T03:23:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2011/03/29/disaster-2-0-innovation-in-the-disaster-response-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the United Nations released their report "Disaster Relief 2.0: The Future of Information Sharing in Humanitarian Emergencies."  Two members of the <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a> were interviewed for this report, myself and Nicolas Chavent.   Also of course many other from friend and partner organizations were interviewed as well.</p>

<p>For anyone interested in open data or new methods of crisis response I recommend you read the <a href="http://issuu.com/unfoundation/docs/disaster_relief20_report">whole report</a>.  For others, well a seventy-two page report might seem like a bit much so what might be key is the <a href="http://www.unfoundation.org/assets/pdf/disaster-relief-2-findings-1.pdf">recommendations</a>.  Key is the idea that information communities (called V&amp;TC in the report) came together after the earthquake in Haiti to help.  Much of this revolved around the sharing and collection of data.  The value of this type of activity to make a difference was clearly shown.  The real question though is how do you make this happen again?  And how can this fit into a framework that makes sense from the perspective of the large organizations as well as the informal communities.</p>

<p>The recommendations suggest a method so that the V&amp;TCs and the traditional humanitarian system can work together.  This includes 5 parts:</p>

<p>"1. A neutral forum to surface areas of agreement and conflict between international humanitarian system and the V&amp;TCs.
2. An innovation space where new tools and practices can be explored as experiments, allowing for the failures that are a necessary component of learning new ways of working.
3. A deployable field team with a mandate to deploy the best available tools and practices from the V&amp;TCs to the field.
4. A research and training consortium to evaluate the work in the field and to train humanitarians and V&amp;TCs alike in the best practices for information management in a humanitarian context.
5. A clear operational interface that outlines ways of collaborating before and during emergencies, with agreed procedures for communication, shared standards for data exchange and an understanding of roles, priorities and capabilities"</p>

<p>One of the key differences between technologists experimenting within the humanitarian response space versus a traditional technology start-up is the cost of failure.  Remember in the early days of  Twitter when things went down all the time?  Or other technologies that didn't work quite right?  Well, usually the risk is to shareholders, in crisis response this failure can translate to lives.    Hence the recommendation of a neutral space, an experimental zone, a deployment team and a way to communicate successes and failures back.  In some ways this is taking what people were already doing in informal ways and giving it formal pathways.</p>

<p>I think much as new technologies replace old in the start-up space there will still be innovation from outside within the crisis response space.  If the innovation space is working in an optimum setting it will be able to operationalize these techniques coming up outside the formal structures.  Though I suspect some will still slip through, since when there is an emergency people will use what is simple, they know and what works.  No matter what I think if these recommendations are adopted it will be a step forward in bringing the formal and informal groups together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenStreetMap in the First Month After the Haiti Quake]]></title>
    <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2010/09/06/openstreetmap-in-the-first-month-after-the-haiti-quake/"/>
    <updated>2010-09-06T10:39:39+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2010/09/06/openstreetmap-in-the-first-month-after-the-haiti-quake</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>There is no question the collaboration of the OpenStreetMap community in the month following the earthquake in Haiti was amazing.  People from all over the world traced satellite imagery and imported data to create comprehensive street data for Port-au-Prince and the rest of the earthquake affected parts of the country.  After reading <a href="http://www.ethanzuckerman.com/blog/2010/09/02/crisis-commons-and-the-challenges-of-distributed-disaster-response/">this Ethan Zuckerman blog post</a>, I wanted to do some analysis of who exactly made the map. Was it primarily the already existing <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org">OpenStreetMap</a> community?  Or was it those who didn't want to just text message their ten dollars and actually wanted to do something to help and OpenStreetMap became a venue for that?  This new group would mostly individuals coming from <a href="http://crisiscommons.org/">CrisisCommons</a> during the many CrisisCamps that occurred during this time.  I've always stated that it was the already existing OpenStreetMap community that did the majority of the map, but I was going on gut instinct, not actual statistics and facts.</p>

<p>What was lacking to provide facts and statistics was an analysis of the edits that occurred in the first month in Haiti.  Ian Dees was nice enough to download the daily edits from January 12th through Feburary 11th for me and put them in a SQLite database.  If you wish to do your own analysis that database is available <a href="http://www.maploser.com/edits.sqlite">here</a>.  I did all of my analysis in SQLite with queries, except for the graphs you see, which were created in OpenOffice.  It should also be noted that editing a node within the context of my analysis means either creating, deleting or changing a node.  A node for those not fluent in OSM terminology is essentially a point.  Multiple nodes strung together create lines and a series of nodes that connect back to each other create polygons.  So here is a somewhat belated but I believe necessary analysis.</p>

<p>The first OSM users to edit in Haiti after the earthquake were <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/user/ikiya">ikiya</a> and <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/user/lyx">lyx</a>.  What I thought was striking is that they live on opposite sides of the world, one in Japan and the other in Germany.  They began editing at 9:00 GMT January 13th, 12 hours after the earthquake occurred.  Other than the first editors I also looked at information on the most edits from various perspectives.</p>

<p>The most total editors in an hour was 41 which occurred on January 24th at 16:00 GMT,  8,531 nodes were edited that hour.  The most nodes ever edited in a single hour during this time was 39,523 by 28 people on Saturday, January 16th at 17:02:10 GMT.  Though it should be noted 33,000 of those nodes were the import of Haiti boundaries.  The next highest amount of node edits was at Wed, February 10th 2010 21:02:09 GMT with only 5 people editing a total of 25,098 nodes.  The individual who had the most edits who wasn’t the Haiti_boundaries_import user was <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/user/rab">rab</a>.  Though these various leader boards of edits are interesting they do not answer my initial question.  Who made the majority of the contribution to the map?  Those who were already existing OpenStreetMap contributors or those that began editing OpenStreetMap specifically after the earthquake in Haiti.</p>

<p>Of the top 40 editors in terms of number of nodes edited during the first month only 1 signed up after the earthquake, everyone else was already an OSM user before.  Total editors during this time period was 605, though it should be noted a handful were bots and imports.  The total editors who signed up after the quake was 230 and they edited 206,682 nodes for an average of 244 nodes edited per user.  Of those 65,390 were by the <a href="http://www.openstreetmap.org/user/Haiti_boundaries_import">Haiti_boundaries_import</a> user.  The contributors who signed up before the earthquake contributed edits to 1,215,510 nodes for an average of 267 nodes edited each.  The total number of nodes edited during this first month as 1,422,205.  The top 10 contributors edited 471,520 of these nodes.  On the other end of the spectrum were those that edited a single node, 183 accounts total.  Of those 183 there were 52 that signed up after the earthquake and 130 before.</p>

<p>To better display the various breakdowns of edits by day I created a series of line graphs.  Each graph contains values by all editors, editors who signed up before the earthquake and editors who signed up after the earthquake.  The line labeled "Column B" is always all editors, "Column C" those that signed up afterward the earthquake and "Column D" those that signed up before the earthquake.</p>

<p>[caption id="" align="aligncenter" width="597" caption="Total Nodes Edited per Day"]<img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4130/4962791275_dab2906600_o.png" alt="Total Nodes Edited per Day" />[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="" align="aligncenter" width="623" caption="Average Nodes Edited per User By Day"]<img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4133/4962784755_a61a964928_o.png" alt="Average Nodes Edited per User By Day" />[/caption]</p>

<p>[caption id="" align="aligncenter" width="601" caption="Total Users Editing per Day"]<img src="http://farm5.static.flickr.com/4087/4963374550_e7562f8d95_o.png" alt="Total Users Editing per Day" />[/caption]</p>

<p>From looking at different breakdowns of the edits that occurred in the month after the earthquake in Haiti one can see that the majority of the data edited came from the already existing OpenStreetMap Community.  85% of nodes edited in Haiti during this month were by those with already existing OpenStreetMap accounts.  Not only were the majority of the nodes, but also the majority of editors, a total of 375.  The new contributors did make a contribution to OpenStreetMap during this time, but the vast majority of edits were by those already using OSM.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team Mission 3 to Haiti - Day 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2010/06/14/humanitarian-openstreetmap-team-mission-3-to-haiti-day-1/"/>
    <updated>2010-06-14T17:41:02+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://wonderchook.github.com/maploser/blog/2010/06/14/humanitarian-openstreetmap-team-mission-3-to-haiti-day-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I'm off on a 2 and a half week trip with the <a href="http://wiki.openstreetmap.org/wiki/Humanitarian_OSM_Team">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a> in Haiti. After the earthquake in January OpenStreetMap proved to be an invaluable basemap of Haiti.  Initially all of the edits were occurring remotely from all over the world.  The community within OSM created various extracts of the data used by GIS Analysts, USARS teams and many others working on the ground and from afar.  The amazing collaboration during that time has been captured in various blog posts and<a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fJvR84UX5RI"> conference talks.
</a>
Now that actions have switched from immediate emergency to rebuilding and cleanup the goals of the Humanitarian OpenStreetMap team have changed some as well.  Our focus is on capacity building and training those working on the ground.  Through intensive all day training sessions we lead groups from data collection with GPS and Walking Papers to editing within JOSM (Java OpenStreetMap Editor).  Following up on two previous missions that included mapping within Port-au-Prince and Jacmel our intent is to continue moving outward into other cities within Haiti.  Now that hurricane season is upon us building this mapping capacity is more important than ever.</p>

<p>Preparation for our trip proved intensive.  There were vaccines to obtain, equipment to procure and training materials to create and review.  I was primarily responsible for creating more H.O.T. Kits as we call them.  A H.O.T. Kit is a pelican case containing a printer/scanner, a laptop, GPS units, batteries and an external hard drive for data.  Currently there are already two such kits in Haiti left behind from previous missions, but as we expand into other areas the need for more kits was clear.  The kits are left behind in country after the H.O.T. Team leaves to continued editing and collection of OpenStreetMap data can happen.  There was no additional budget for more kits for this mission. Fortunately the community once again proved amazing, I was able to raise <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org/weblog/?page_id=13">$1000.00 for GPS units</a> and ESRI donated laptops.</p>

<p>The Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team wouldn't be anything without the people.  We are following up on the amazing groundwork laid by <a href="http://dbsgeo.com/">Dane Springmeyer</a>,<a href="http://developmentseed.org/team/robert-soden"> Robert Soden</a> and Nicolas Chavent on two previous missions.  This mission includes the amazing guidance of Nicolas Chavent bringing his invaluable experience from the previous two missions as well as three new actors including myself, <a href="http://toddhuffman.pbworks.com/">Todd Huffman</a> and <a href="http://ellermann.net/">Trevor Ellermann</a>.  Everyone brings their own unique experiences and skills to the team.  Nicolas and his key GIS and humanitarian experience, myself with my experience in mapping in a variety of field conditions with many types of data.  Todd's creativity solving problems in unique ways in difficult environments and Trevor's technical skills in system administration and programming.</p>

<p>Naturally the most compelling reason I felt to join this mission was to help.   Having the opportunity to assist in a more hands on way than I have previously is a privilege.  The secondary but more personally compelling reason I felt to go to Haiti is to see the land I've spent the past months intensively mapping, discussing and coordinating data around.  The only comparable effort I was involved in was during Katrina five years ago.  I didn't actually visit New Orleans until a month ago, even five years later to experience the land I spent so much time looking at above was a learning experience.  You learn so much more about imagery interpretation and data analysis by actually being in the environment you are analyzing.  I hope that my trip will enable me to be even more effective in the future in other response efforts.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
