<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: haiti | Kate Chapman - Maploser]]></title>
  <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/categories/haiti/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://maploser.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-11-30T16:45:51+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://maploser.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kate Chapman]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Disaster 2.0, Innovation in the Disaster Response Space]]></title>
    <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/2011/03/29/disaster-2-0-innovation-in-the-disaster-response-space/"/>
    <updated>2011-03-29T03:23:12+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://maploser.com/blog/2011/03/29/disaster-2-0-innovation-in-the-disaster-response-space</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Today the United Nations released their report "Disaster Relief 2.0: The Future of Information Sharing in Humanitarian Emergencies."  Two members of the <a href="http://hot.openstreetmap.org">Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team</a> were interviewed for this report, myself and Nicolas Chavent.   Also of course many other from friend and partner organizations were interviewed as well.</p>

<p>For anyone interested in open data or new methods of crisis response I recommend you read the <a href="http://issuu.com/unfoundation/docs/disaster_relief20_report">whole report</a>.  For others, well a seventy-two page report might seem like a bit much so what might be key is the <a href="http://www.unfoundation.org/assets/pdf/disaster-relief-2-findings-1.pdf">recommendations</a>.  Key is the idea that information communities (called V&amp;TC in the report) came together after the earthquake in Haiti to help.  Much of this revolved around the sharing and collection of data.  The value of this type of activity to make a difference was clearly shown.  The real question though is how do you make this happen again?  And how can this fit into a framework that makes sense from the perspective of the large organizations as well as the informal communities.</p>

<p>The recommendations suggest a method so that the V&amp;TCs and the traditional humanitarian system can work together.  This includes 5 parts:</p>

<p>"1. A neutral forum to surface areas of agreement and conflict between international humanitarian system and the V&amp;TCs.
2. An innovation space where new tools and practices can be explored as experiments, allowing for the failures that are a necessary component of learning new ways of working.
3. A deployable field team with a mandate to deploy the best available tools and practices from the V&amp;TCs to the field.
4. A research and training consortium to evaluate the work in the field and to train humanitarians and V&amp;TCs alike in the best practices for information management in a humanitarian context.
5. A clear operational interface that outlines ways of collaborating before and during emergencies, with agreed procedures for communication, shared standards for data exchange and an understanding of roles, priorities and capabilities"</p>

<p>One of the key differences between technologists experimenting within the humanitarian response space versus a traditional technology start-up is the cost of failure.  Remember in the early days of  Twitter when things went down all the time?  Or other technologies that didn't work quite right?  Well, usually the risk is to shareholders, in crisis response this failure can translate to lives.    Hence the recommendation of a neutral space, an experimental zone, a deployment team and a way to communicate successes and failures back.  In some ways this is taking what people were already doing in informal ways and giving it formal pathways.</p>

<p>I think much as new technologies replace old in the start-up space there will still be innovation from outside within the crisis response space.  If the innovation space is working in an optimum setting it will be able to operationalize these techniques coming up outside the formal structures.  Though I suspect some will still slip through, since when there is an emergency people will use what is simple, they know and what works.  No matter what I think if these recommendations are adopted it will be a step forward in bringing the formal and informal groups together.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Talk: Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team in Haiti]]></title>
    <link href="http://maploser.com/blog/2010/11/18/talk-humanitarian-openstreetmap-team-in-haiti/"/>
    <updated>2010-11-18T05:37:47+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://maploser.com/blog/2010/11/18/talk-humanitarian-openstreetmap-team-in-haiti</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Back in the beginning of October I attended the <a href="http://www.crisismappers.net/page/iccm-2010-haiti-and-beyond">International Conference on Crisis Mapping</a>.  The first day of the event was open to the public and included many ignite talks on a variety of topics related to crisis response.  I gave a talk titled "Humanitarian OpenStreetMap Team in Haiti: from Crisis to Capacity Building."  I highlighted how HOT has been working to transfer the maintenance of the Haiti portion of the map to Haiti as well as some ways the data is currently being used.</p>

<p>See for yourself:</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
